Guide to the Charles Edward Jefferson Papers circa 1882-1941 MS 3049
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Charles Edward Jefferson papers
circa 1882-1941
MS 3049
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
2.92 Linear feet in four document boxes and one box for small booklets
The collection primarily includes sermons, lectures, and other writings of Charles Edward Jefferson (1860-1937). Jefferson was pastor of Broadway Tabernacle Church in New York City from 1898 to 1929, and the bulk of the collection dates from his years at that church, though the audience for many of these writings range beyond the attendees at his church services. Many of these materials are in their published form, including those on pacifism and anti-militarism in the years leading to World War I, but there are also several sermons and lectures in their original typescript form. The collection also includes Jefferson's notes on biblical texts, letters of congratulations on his 25th anniversary at Broadway Tabernacle, some Broadway Tabernacle year books, and other documents.
Jefferson, Charles Edward, 1860-1937
Scope and Contents note
The collection primarily includes sermons, lectures, and other writings of Charles Edward Jefferson (1860-1937). Jefferson was pastor of Broadway Tabernacle Church between 1898-1930, and the bulk of the collection dates from his years at that church. Many of these materials are in their published form, but there are also several sermons and lectures in their original typescript form. Among the materials are Jefferson's sermon at his installation as pastor, at a memorial service for assassinated U.S. president William McKinley, many of the sermons he delivered annually to the boys and girls of Broadway Tabernacle, his writings on pacifism and amti-militarism, and three essays on nature inspired by land he owned in New Hampshire.
The collection also includes some of Jefferson's notes on biblical texts, a record of some marriages he performed, and letters of congratulations from parishioners and associates on his 25th anniversary at Broadway Tabernacle. There is also some print matter related to Broadway Tabernacle itself including, among other documents, some year books and an Endowment Fund appeal.
Arrangement Note
The collection is organized in two series:
Series I. Sermons, Lectures, & Other Writings (circa 1882-1937)
Series II. Other Documents (1898-1941)
Biographical/Historical Note
Charles Edward Jefferson (1860-1937) was born in Cambridge, Ohio. He attended Ohio Wesleyan University, graduating in 1882 and then taking the position of superintendent of public schools in Worthington, Ohio. He entered Boston University in 1884, briefly at its law school before moving to BU's School of Theology, from which he graduated in 1887. Shortly after graduating, he began work as pastor of the Central Congregational Church in Chelsea, Massachusetts. He remained there until early 1898 when he resigned to become the pastor of Broadway Tabernacle Church in New York City on 19 April. The materials in this collection date largely from Jefferson's years at Broadway Tabernacle.
Broadway Tabernacle was founded in 1840. Jefferson was the congregation's fifth pastor. At the time of his installation, the church was located at Broadway and 34th Street in Manhattan. It moved to Broadway and 56th Street in 1905 where it remained until 1969. The congregation is now known as the Broadway United Church of Christ and is located on West 86th Street in New York.
Jefferson was pastor of Broadway Tabernacle for 31 years, resigning in 1929. He traveled and spoke widely, and was well known for his advocacy of pacifism, particularly in the years leading to America's involvement in World War I.
(The above note was based largely on a 1922 biographical sketch of Jefferson found in the collection and information on the website of the Broadway United Church of Christ.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
Gift of Teddy Jefferson, January 2018.
Related Archival Materials Note
N-YHS also holds the Broadway Tabernacle Church and Society Papers, 1835-1980 (MS 74).
Broadway Tabernacle (New York, N.Y.).; Jefferson, Charles Edward, 1860-1937; Congregational churches -- New York (State) -- New York.; Congregationalism -- Clergy; Lectures; Sermons; Writings (documents)
- Series I. Sermons, Lectures, & Other Writings, circa 1882-1937; 2.4 Linear feet
  Arrangement Note
  The series is organized in two subseries:
  Subseries I.A. Manuscript Writings
  Subseries II.B. Published Writings
  Scope and Contents Note
  The series includes a number of Charles Edward Jefferson's sermons, lectures, and other writings. Most are in a printed, published form, but several are in typed manuscript form. Most of these were delivered to the parishioners of Broadway Tabernacle Church, but other audiences are represented here as well. The container lists include all the titles of the pieces in the series.
  - Subseries I.A. Manuscript Writings, circa 1882-1937; 0.63 Linear feet
    The subseries is arranged with Jefferson's sermons in manuscript form first, in chronological order, followed by notebooks and annotated texts. Many of the sermons are numbered, and that number is included in parentheses in the container list.
    The subseries primarily includes typed manuscripts of some of Charles Edward Jefferson's sermons and lectures. These represent only a small number (21) of the sermons he delivered in his lifetime, but include the paper he read at his installation as pastor at Broadway Tabernacle Church in 1898. The papers often indicate the place and audience to which they were given, including universities and other schools, the Young Women's Club of Broadway Tabernacle, other churches, and other venues. Some of the remarks were delivered at various times and these were noted on the paper; this was especially true for "Old Texts Under New Skies" which records 35 deliveries from New York to California and from Montreal to Alabama. Some of the typed texts include handwritten changes.
    The subseries also includes manuscript forms of some of Jefferson's other writings including a poem, three essays on nature inspired by land he owned in New Hampshire, and three notebooks and an annotated handbook concerning biblical texts.
    - Paper Read at Installation of Jefferson as Pastor of Broadway Tabernacle (#-50), 1898 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Commencement Oration at Delaware, Ohio (#343), 1900 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Emerson and Carlyle (#615), 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Martin Luther (#714), 1904 April 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - John Calvin (#739), 1904 November 26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - John Knox (#834), 1905 November 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Congregationalism: Past, Present & Future (#968), 1907 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "All things are yours" (#1248), 1910 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - John Ruskin (#1269), 1910 November 28 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Samuel Johnson (#1344), 1911, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - John Bunyan (#162-), 1914, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - The Mission of Hobab (#1949), 1917 December 2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Vicarious Suffering (#1948), 1917 December 2 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - The Things of God: III. The Holy Catholic Church (#2105), 1918 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Robert Browning (#2132), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - China, 1926 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Old Texts Under New Skies (#2716), 1926-1934 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - The Mind of Lindbergh (#2792), 1927 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - John Ruskin (#2947), 1929 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - The Rich Young Ruler, 1931-1937 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - What Do You Think of God?, 1931-1937 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - It is Raining (Poem), 1930 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - No. 1: My Eight Acres, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - No. 3: Grass, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - No. 7: Snow, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - The Psalms, Vol. I (Notebook), undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - [Notes on New Testament], undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Notebook includes notes on the text of the Gospels of the New Testament, including comparisons of content, of differences in particular narrative scenes, characteristics of each Book, etc.
    - [Notebook], 1908-1909 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Includes the marketing form of Jefferson's booklet "The Old Year and the New," which has the cloth cover design and interior blank pages. Under the heading "The Beautiful," the first few blank pages have entries for various days from 1908 June 8 to 1909 January 29 with various observations.
    - Minister's Hand-Book (annotated), circa 1882? (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Includes a copy of the second edition of Savage's "Minister's Hand-Book," with Jefferson's notes and annotations.
  - Subseries II.B. Published Writings, 1899-1936; 1.77 Linear feet
    The container list below is arranged, with one set of exceptions, in chronological order. The one exception are the annual sermons Jefferson delivered to the boys and girls of Broadway Tabernacle; these are presented together in chronological order at the end of the container list. Because of the wide range of sizes of the documents, the booklets and books themselves were boxed in an appropriate manner for storage and, as can be discerned from the various box numbers in the container list, do not strictly follow the order as presented in the list.
    The subseries includes the sermons, essays, and other writings of Charles Edward Jefferson that appeared in printed form. Most of these took the form of small booklets. Among these are Jefferson's remarks at the memorial service for assassinated U.S. president William McKinley, his expressions of pcifism and anti-militarism in the years around World War I, the annual sermons he delivered to the boys and girls of Broadway Tabernacle, a biographical sketch (1922), his reflections on Congregationalism, and other topics. Many of the booklets have multiple copies, as many as five copies in some cases.
    - The Person of Christ, 1899 (Box 5)
    - Sermon at the 73rd Anniversary of the American Seamen's Friend Society, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Address at the Memorial Service for President William McKinley, 1901 (Box 5)
    - Congregationalism: Its Origin, Principles and Mission, 1901 (Box 5)
    - 60th Anniversary of Broadway Tabernacle Church, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Includes two booklets: "The Broadway Tabernacle of the Past and Future," by Jefferson and a program of the week's events (January 16-23), with two images of the interiors of the old and new buildings.
    - Congregationalism: Its Contribution to Education, 1902 (Box 5)
    - Things Fundamental: A Course of Thirteen Discourses in Modern Apologetics, 1903 (Box 3, Volume 1)
    - The Puritan and the Home, 1904 (Box 5)
    - Fundamentals, 1907 (Box 3, Volume 2)
      Published by the Young Men's Christian Association Press.
    - The Next Step, 1909 (Box 3, Volume 3)
    - The Puritan Conscience, 1909 (Box 5)
    - The Delusion of Militarism, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Reprint from the Atlantic Monthly, 1909 March.
    - Missions and International Peace, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Congregationalism (2 copies), 1910 (Box 3, Volume 4-5)
    - A Message to the Perplexed, 1913 (Box 5)
    - A New Year's Sermon, 1914 (Box 5)
    - The Nemesis of Armaments, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Published by the New York Peace Society; reprint from The Independent, 1914 August 17.
    - Three Men Behind the Guns, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Published by the American Association for International Conciliation.
    - The Cause of the War, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Includes two versions of the booklet, one published by the Church Peace Union as the first in a series of papers under the heading of "The Church and International Peace." The second version was published by Thomas Y. Crowell Co.
    - The Puritan and the Cavalier, 1914 (Box 5)
    - A Great Church in a Great City (Broadway Tabernacle's 75th Anniversary), 1915 (Box 5)
    - What Armed Peace Leads To, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Ethical Questions Created by Our Government's Declaration of War, 1917 (Box 5)
    - Jefferson's 20th Anniversary Discourse, 1918 (Box 3, Volume 6)
    - The Question Which Answers Itself, 1918 (Box 5)
    - A New Year's Sermon: Removing Mountains, 1920 (Box 5)
    - Pilgrim Tercentenary Sermon, 1920 (Box 5)
    - A New Year's Sermon: Stand Upon They Feet, 1921 (Box 5)
    - Biographical Sketch of Charles Edward Jefferson, 1922 (Box 5)
    - The Heavenly Vision, 1922 (Box 5)
    - "Come, Let Us Reason Together", 1922 (Box 5)
    - The Appeal of the Christian Ministry, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - The Friendship Indispensable, 1923 (Box 3, Volume 7)
    - New Men and New Years, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Faith, 1924 (Box 5)
    - "I Don't Know What I Believe", 1926 (Box 5)
    - The Puritan, 1926 (Box 5)
    - Expectancy / "Maranatha", 1927 (Box 5)
    - Streams in the Desert, 1927 (Box 5)
    - Like a Trumpet, 1927 (Box 5)
    - Thinking Peace, 1927 (Box 5)
    - The Next Step, 1928? (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Undated reprint (International Peace Series, Number 6) by the World Alliance for International Friendship Through the Churches of Jefferson's 1928 sermon preached on the tenth anniversary of the signing of the armistice ending World War I.
    - Jefferson's 30th Anniversary at Broadway Tabernacle, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Includes two booklets: Jefferson's sermon preached on the occasion of his 30th anniversary (3 copies) and "Thirty Years on Broadway."
    - The One Foundation, 1929 (Box 5)
    - Obedience to Law, 1929 (Box 5)
    - A Charge to the Officers of the Young People's Society of Christian Endeavor, 1929 (Box 5)
    - Watch Night Sermon: Facing the Future, 1929 (Box 5)
    - "I remember the days of old." Psalms 143.5, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - [The Character of Jesus], 1935 (Box 4, Volume 8)
      Book translated into Czech. Inscribed to Jefferson by the translator. Pages uncut.
    - Acknowledging Our Blessings, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Sermons to the Boys and Girls of the Broadway Tabernacle (Box -)
    - The Duty of Asking Questions, 1902 (Box 5)
    - My Father's Business, 1904 (Box 5)
    - The Silent Years, 1905 (Box 5)
    - Work, 1906 (Box 5)
    - The Will, 1907 (Box 5)
    - Honesty, 1908 (Box 5)
    - Being A Christian, 1909 (Box 5)
    - The Sin of Untruthfulness, 1910 (Box 5)
    - Lions and Adders, 1911 (Box 5)
    - A Brave Builder, 1912 (Box 5)
    - The Two Roads, 1913 (Box 5)
    - The Tongue, 1914 (Box 5)
    - Preparedness, 1916 (Box 5)
    - Discipline, 1917 (Box 5)
    - Foundations of Sapphires, 1918 (Box 5)
    - Wings, 1919 (Box 5)
    - The Mayflower, 1920 (Box 5)
    - Five Wrong Ideas of God, 1921 (Box 5)
    - Play, 1923 (Box 5)
    - The Wedge of Gold, 1924 (Box 5)
    - Jonah, 1925 (Box 5)
    - What the Chairs Say, 1926 (Box 5)
    - The Most Beautiful Thing in the World, 1927 (Box 5)
    - War, 1928 (Box 5)
    - Our Little Brothers and Sisters, 1929 (Box 5)
    - Fun, 1930 (Box 5)
- Series II. Other Documents, 1898-1941; 0.52 Linear feet
  The series includes documents from the collection other than Jefferson's sermons and writings. Some of these relate directly to Jefferson, including a record of some marriage ceremonies he performed and congratulatory letters he received on the occasion of his 25th anniversary at Broadway Tabernacle. Other documents relate to the church itself, including an appeal for the Endowment Fund (circa 1900?), an information pamphlet (1902), and some Year Books. There are also a small number of documents not related directly to either Jefferson or Broadway Tabernacle. The container list identifies all content.
  The subseries is arranged topically, first with material related directly to Jefferson, followed by that related to Broadway Tabernacle generally, and concluding with miscellaneous items.
  - Photographs, circa 1900, 1930? (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes two portrait photographs of Jefferson.
  - Sermon Booklet / Loose Paper Slips, circa 1904 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Includes a copy of the published sermon to the boys and girls of Broadway Tabernacle of 1904 May 8. Tucked between many of the booklet pages are very small slips of paper with names, codes, and impressionistic facial sketches. Other slips have dollar amounts noted on them. Use caution in handling the booklet in order not to lose the small slips.
  - Marriage Ceremony Record Stubs, 1898-1900 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Record of 10 marriages (numbered 10-19) performed by Jefferson.
  - Annotated Epistles, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Includes a pocket size copy of some New Testament epistles, with annotations.
  - Christmas Builders, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Includes binding and unprinted pages for Jefferson's book.
  - Jefferson's 25th Anniversary. Bound Congratulatory Letters from Parishioners, 1923 (Box 4, Volume 18)
  - Jefferson's 25th Anniversary. Bound Congratulatory Letters from Associates and Friends, 1923 (Box 4, Volume 19)
  - Broadway Tabernacle Church. Endowment Funds, circa 1900? (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Broadway Tabernacle Church Information Pamphlet, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Broadway Tabernacle Church Year Book, 1898 (Box 4, Volume 9)
  - Broadway Tabernacle Church Year Book, 1920-1928 (Box 4, Volume 10-17)
    Includes books for 1920, 1921, 1922, 1924, 1926, 1927, 1928 (2 copies).
  - Broadway Tabernacle Tidings, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Manhattan Congregational Church 13th Annual Report, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "The God of War." Poem by Israel Zangwill, circa 1911 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Practical Guide No. 10: Correcting Weight and Figure, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Booklet is part of "Twelve Weeks to Health," the Arthur A. McGovern Course in Health Building by Practical Hygiene, Organic Stimulation and Functional Re-Education.